Guide to Culinary Ephemera: Flour Products, Leavening Agents, and Baked Goods ams.0058
University of Michigan Library (Special Collections Research Center)
- Flour Products
  - Box 33.
    - Golden rule presents the following special light-nin' biscuit flour recipes: [folded brochure], circa 1930s (Box 33, Folder 27)
      Item [27] includes mention of (Mrs. W.H.) Ella Mae Ives, director of the radio cookery department for the Columbus Dispatch. Recipes use biscuit mix.
    - Hospitality in a "Jiffy." 13 p., circa 1960s (Box 33, Folder 28)
      Item [28] promotes Jiffy mixes. Includes inside front cover illustration of mill; back cover illustrations of product packages. Recipes for carrot bread, grasshopper pie with liquor, chocolate fondue, and pizza.
    - Freshest ideas from Pillsbury. [12] p., 1990 (Box 33, Folder 29)
      Item [29] celebrates birthday of Pillsbury doughboy. Includes photographs of Poppin' Fresh; product coupons; and order form for theme toys. All recipes use packaged doughs.
    - $50,000 prize-winner, $10,000 prize-winner, $4,000 prize-winner: [folded brochure], circa 1950s (Box 33, Folder 30)
      Item [30] promotes Pillsbury flour. Includes illustrations of prize winners and printed signature of Ann Pillsbury. Recipes for cake, cookies,and rolls.
    - Pillsbury hot roll mix baking book. 65 p., circa 1970s (Box 33, Folder 31)
      Item [31] includes tips for yeast baking and freezing, and section on baking for two. Directions for shaping rolls. Recipes for raised doughnuts, kolacky, spicy barbeque pizza, and bacon patio crax.
    - Minute success around the clock: [folded brochure], circa 1970s (Box 33, Folder 32)
      Item [32] promotes Pillsbury refrigerated doughs. Includes mention of Ann Pillsbury consumer service kitchens and tips for using and keeping packaged doughs. Recipes for frosted coffee ring, cheese 'n' wiener crescents, and butterflake herb loaf.
    - Take a coffee break with Pillsbury's coffee time mixes. [16] p., circa 1970s (Box 33, Folder 33)
      Item [33] promotes Pillsbury mixes. This item is similar to item [14]. Contains recipes for fruit and nut breads.
    - Come one! Come all! to the cookie carnival: do your own thing with cookies! 12 p., circa 1970s (Box 33, Folder 34)
      Item [34] promotes Marion-Kay flavorings and spices. Similar to [17]. From Indiana State Fair. Recipe pages are perforated into recipe cards. Contains explanations of ingredients and techniques. Recipes for cookies, linzer torte, one Indian recipe for gulab jamun.
  - Box 34.
    Orton, Vrest, 1897-1986.
    White, Martha.
    WLS (Radio station: Chicago, Ill.)
    Ismert-Hincke Milling Co.
    Bluff City Mills.
    Michigan. Department of Health.
    Lawrenceburg Roller Mills Company.
    International Milling Company, Inc.
    Henkel Flour Mills.
    Vermont Guild of Oldtime Crafts and Industries, Inc.
    Martha White Foods.
    Durum Wheat Institute.
    - Christmas treats: holiday recipes from farm kitchens. 8 p., circa 1950s (Box 34, Folder 1)
      Item [1] attributes responsibility to Prairie farmer-WLS Women's Section. Recipes are attributed to named members of staff. Sample recipes include: popcorn cake, no-bake fruit cake, date roll.
    - Hospitality in a "Jiffy". 21 p., circa 1970s (Box 34, Folder 2)
      Item [2] promotes Jiffy baking mixes. Inside front cover illustration of factory. Back cover has illustrations of packaging. All recipes use Jiffy baking mixes. Gives hints for microwaving cakes. Sample recipes include: tuna cornbread pizza, pineapple bread, cardamon cake.
    - Bread making illustrated and tested recipes / Mary Ann Flour. 1 v. (unpaged), circa 1930s (Box 34, Folder 3)
      Item [3] promotes Mary Ann flour. Mentions ice box in recipes. Includes bread recipes using dried yeast and compressed yeast. Recipes include illustration of process. Sample recipes: bread making with overnight sponge, quick parker house rolls.
    - Good recipes, the first rule for cake success. 62 + p., circa 1934 (Box 34, Folder 4)
      Item [4] promotes Swans Down cake flour. Illustrations of packaging for Swans Down, Diamond Crystal salt, Calumet baking powder. Recipes include illustration of process. Sample recipes: Lord Baltimore cake, gold cookies, sea foam frosting. Includes sections with baking and frosting hints. Includes calendar of cakes for holidays, events and occasions. Library's copy imperfect, all before p. 4 wanting, all after p. 62 wanting; appears to be "The latest cake secrets" 1934, based on p. 157 of "Collecting cookbooks."
    - A few choice recipes for bread, cake, biscuits: better than necessary. 1 v. (unpaged), circa 1920s (Box 34, Folder 5)
      Item [5] promotes I-H best patent flour. Front cover has illustration of packaging. Includes bread recipes using dried yeast and compressed yeast. Sample recipes include: devil's food cake, yeast foam bread, potato cake.
    - 55 favorite Ann Pillsbury cake recipes. 64 p., 1952 (Box 34, Folder 6)
      Item [6] promotes Sno Sheen cake flour. Front cover has illustration of Kate Smith and promotes her show on NBC-TV. Front cover illustration of serving suggestion. Inside back cover offer for Lady Ann pattern Rogers silverplate and cake pan. Gives process and recipe for quick-mix shortening cake.
    - 25 easy recipes with self-rising flour and self-rising corn meal. 17 p., 1960 (Box 34, Folder 7)
      Item [7] includes recipes using basic mix for muffins and biscuits, with variations. Includes recipes for basic yeast batter, with variations. Sample recipes: corn meal waffles, refrigerator rolls, chocolate toffee squares.
    - Tasty foods using flour. Rev. ed. 12 p., 1964 (Box 34, Folder 8)
      Item [8] includes recipes using basic mix for biscuits, with variations. Sample recipes: white batter bread, whole wheat coffeecake, rolled-wheat cake. Back cover stamped "Dearborn Health Dept."
    - Tid-bits from town talk: a few reliable suggestions for conjuring with the staff of life. 47 p., 1906 (Box 34, Folder 9)
      Item [9] promotes Town Talk flour. Back cover illustration of packaging. Front cover illustration of female baker and stove. Some recipes include liquor. Sample recipes: puffy popovers, beefsteak pate, demon cake. Includes table of equivalents, including gills and saltspoonfuls.
    - Good things to bake with Wheatsworth flour: [folded brochure], circa 1930s (Box 34, Folder 10)
      Item [10] has front cover illustration of packaging. Illustrations of serving suggestions accompany some recipes.
    - Good things to eat made with Velvet Cake and Pastry Flour. 26 p., 1954 (Box 34, Folder 11)
      Item [11] has back cover illustration of packaging, shows names Robin Hood Flour and Henkel Flour Mills. Inside front cover illustration of Detroit factory, with figures for milling and storage capacities. Includes recipes for four kinds of devil's food cake.
    - Vermont Guild recipes for old-fashioned stoneground corn meal, wheat meal, samp cereal, cracked wheat, and muffin meal. 16 p., 1942 (Box 34, Folder 12)
      Item [12] has an introduction by Vrest Orton. Vermont brown bread recipe has variations for sweet milk and sour milk. Sample recipes include New England corn bread, pioneer's johnny cake.
    - Basically biscuits: how to make perfect biscuits and their delicious variations / from Martha White: [folded brochure], circa 1980s (Box 34, Folder 13)
      Item [13] promotes Martha White self-rising flour. Recipes include basic biscuit mix, with variations. Sample recipes: sausage roll-ups, cherry turnovers, quick doughnuts.
    - Institute ideas: [newsletter], winter 1975 (Box 34, Folder 14)
      Item [14] is Winter 1975 issue of the newsletter of Wheat Flour Institute. Carries also separate title for this issue: Super snackin'. Illustrations of teenagers with guitars and telephones. Illustrations of serving suggestions accompany some recipes. Sample recipes: fruit cocktail cake, pizza sandwich loaf.
    - Durum wheat notes: [newsletter], winter 1975 (Box 34, Folder 15)
      Item [15] is Winter 1975 issue of the newsletter of Durum Wheat Institute. Carries also separate title for this issue: Hats off to student chefs. Recipes are from Pasta Recipe Contest. Illustrations of serving suggestions accompany recipes. Recipes are attributed to named students.
  - Box 35
    Shane, George C.
    Holmes, Mabel White.
    Glen Mills (Firm: Rowley, Mass.)
    Sleepy Eye Milling Company.
    J.C. Lysle Milling Co.
    George C. Shane Co.
    Wm. Hayden Milling Co.
    - [Glen Mills flour recipes: brochure]., circa 1890s (Box 35, Folder 1)
      Item [1] promotes Glen Mills flour mixtures. Includes product descriptions, advertisements, and directions for use; and recipes for breads, puddings, and desserts. All recipes use products. Sample recipes: Trenton falls pudding, yankee brown bread, and rye drop cakes. Damaged: paper fragile, tearing.
    - Cook book. 96 p., circa 1904 (Box 35, Folder 2)
      Item [2] promotes grain products from Sleepy Eye Milling Company. Includes product descriptions and advertisements; household hints; recipes for breads, desserts, drinks, meats, salads, pickles, and vegetables; and images of Native American mascot and product packaging. Some recipes use product. Some recipes include wine, beer, or liquor as an ingredient. Sample recipes: rolled jelly cake, fricadilla, and corned beef heart. Die cut in loaf shape. 2 copies: only one with cover. Damaged: cover detached, paper fragile, flaking.
    - Washburn-Crosby's Gold Medal, America's greatest family flour: [folded brochure]., 1898 (Box 35, Folder 3)
      Item [3] promotes Washburn-Crosby's flour. Includes product advertisements; account ofshipping quality test; statistics on mill production; and images of product packaging and women in period dress. No recipes. Marked: 6-98. Slip 48-10. Exhibitable advertisement.
    - The measure of good flour: [brochure]., circa 1920 (Box 35, Folder 4)
      Item [4] promotes New Era Mills White Crest Flour from the J.C. Lysle Milling Company. Includes product description and advertisement; recipe for White Crest biscuits; and images of serving suggestion and product packaging. Exhibitable cover.
    - Shane's fine flour: [folded brochure]., circa 1920s (Box 35, Folder 5)
      Item [5] promotes Shane's Fine Flour from George C. Shane Co. Includes product description and advertisement; recipes for breads and desserts; baking hints; and image of product packaging. All recipes use product. Sample recipe: sweet milk griddle cakes.
    - For goodness sake say Ceresota Enriched Flour: [folded brochure]., circa 1940s (Box 35, Folder 6)
      Item [6] promotes Ceresota unbleached flour from Standard Milling Co. Includes product advertisements; recipes for breads and desserts; illustrated offers for gifts and toys with 25 cents and bag label; mail-in coupon; and images of product packaging and men, women and children in period dress. All recipes use product. Sample recipe: father's favorite apple pie. Exhibitable offers.
    - Hospitality in a "Jiffy." 21 p., circa 1970s (Box 35, Folder 7)
      Item [7] promotes Jiffy mixes from Chelsea Milling Company. Includes product advertisement and description of manufacture; recipes for pizzas, casseroles, and desserts; hints for microwave cakes; and images of factory and product packaging. All recipes use products. Sample recipes: biscuit capped tuna, dessert crepes, and fudge mint brownies.
    - "Jiffy" mixes: hospitality in a "Jiffy": recipes. 35 p., circa 1970s (Box 35, Folder 8)
      Item [8] is similar to item [7] but includes redesigned cover; some new recipes; product history; section of microwave recipes; company facts; and index. Sample new recipes: cone-a-cake, microwave caramel corn, and breakfast pizza. Marked: Booklet No. 110194.
    - "Jiffy" mixes: hospitality in a "Jiffy": recipes. 39 p., circa 1970s (Box 35, Folder 9)
      Item [9] is similar to [8] with 4 pages of new recipes. Sample new recipe: spoon bread casserole. Marked: Booklet No. 013197.
    - "Jiffy" mixes: hospitality in a "Jiffy": recipes. 39 p., circa 1970s (Box 35, Folder 10)
      Item [10] is similar to [9] but is marked Booklet No. 081297.
    - Pillsbury's Best Flour: [folded brochure]., circa 1930s (Box 35, Folder 11)
      Item [11] promotes Pillsbury's Best Flour and other products from Pillsbury Flour Mills Company. Includes product descriptions and advertisements; recipes and advice for breads, cake and pie crust; and images of product packaging and serving suggestions. All recipes use product. Sample recipe: bread using dry yeast. Marked: Form 924.
    - The three Rs of wartime baking: rations, 'richment, and recipes / by Mary Ellis Ames: [tabbed brochure]., circa 1943 (Box 35, Folder 12)
      Item [12] promotes Pillsbury's Best Enriched Flour and other products from Pillsbury Flour Mills Company. Includes ration and nutrition advice mentioning food conservation and wartime cooking; product descriptions and advertisements; recipes for breads, entrees, and desserts; and images of product packaging. Sample recipes: canned fruit pie, savory seafood pie, and victory vegetable plate. Tabbed and labeled pages. Marked: POM-2468. Form no. 200M-5-43.
    - The Pillsbury busy lady bake-off recipes. 95 p., 1966 (Box 35, Folder 13)
      Item [13] promotes Pillsbury Best Flour and other products from Pillsbury Company. Includes product advertisement; recipes from the 17th annual Bake-Off for breads, entrees, desserts, and snacks; offer for The Pillsbury family cook book; entry form and rules for Busy Lady Bake-Off; advertisement for General Electric range; images of serving suggestions, product packaging, and women and children in period dress; and index. All recipes use product. Sample recipes: Golden Gate snack bread, ice cream muffins, and Mandarin dream pie. Exhibitable serving suggestions.
    - Yeast breads go modern. 12 p., circa 1960s (Box 35, Folder 14)
      Item [14] promotes Pillsbury No-Knead method of bread making. Includes bread-making hints; storage and freezing advice; recipes for breads, some attributed to Ann Pillsbury; winning recipes from Senior Bake-Off, attributed to Mrs. Grace Sutrey and Mrs. W.L. Carpenter; and images of food preparation. All recipes use product. Sample recipe: No-Knead cinnamon rolls. Loose, 3-hole-punched pages.
    - America's Bake-Off cookbook: 100 winning recipes from Bake-Off 27. 95 p., 1976 (Box 35, Folder 15)
      Item [15] promotes Pillsbury products. Includes 100 winning recipes for breads, entrees, sandwiches and desserts from Bake-Off 27, attributed to individuals; description of Bake-Off; baking hints; artwork commemorating American bicentential; offer for The new Pillsbury family cookbook; advertisement and order form for 1977 Wilton book of cake decorating; images of serving suggestions and men and women in period dress; and index. All recipes use products and include high altitude instructions. Sample recipes: crescent Denver sandwich squares, maple wheat caramel rolls, and apple harvest cake. Exhibitable serving suggestions.
    - [Pillsbury recipe cards]., 1960 (Box 35, Folder 16)
      Item [16] promotes products from the Pillsbury Food Service Division and consists of 9 recipe cards. Includes one quantity cooking recipe per card, two with reference to type A school lunch program. Sample recipe: golden peach crumble.
    - Pillsbury fall planner. 29 p., 2000 (Box 35, Folder 17)
      Item [17] promotes products from Pillsbury Company. Includes foreword from Lola Whalen; advertisements for Pillsbury products; advice for cooking for children; recipes for breakfasts, entrees, sandwiches, snacks, and desserts; menus; offer and order form for Doughboy Store items; and images of serving suggestions,product packaging, and men, women and children in period dress. Most recipes use products. Sample recipes: cinnamon pull apart, chili dog tacos, and ham and cheddar crescents. Exhibitable serving suggestions.
    - Let's bake the Robin-Hood 'no-sift' way / by Rita Martin. 72 p., 1969 (Box 35, Folder 18)
      Item [18] promotes Robin Hood flour from International Milling. Includes product advertisement; information on flour; baking and measurement advice; instructions for CoolRise yeast baking; recipes for breads and desserts; cartoon illustrations; images of food preparation, serving suggestions and product packaging; and index. Most recipes use product. Sample recipes: CoolRise pizza, Swedish butter balls, and peanut butter cookies.
    - Swans Down wants you to meet two friends who will make your cakes even more delicious: [folded brochure]., circa 1930s (Box 35, Folder 19)
      Item [19] promotes Swans Down Cake Flour, Calumet Baking Powder, and Baker's Chocolate. Includes product information and advertisements; dessert recipes; offer and order form for The New Calumet Baking Book and Baker's Best Chocolate Recipes; and images of product packaging. All recipes use products. Sample recipe: three-egg layer cake.
    - Forty roads to health: [brochure]., 1935 (Box 35, Folder 20)
      Item [20] promotes flours from the Wm. Hayden Milling Co. and is an insert to a compilation of 40 whole wheat graham recipes. Includes product advertisement with list of Hayden flours and product packaging illustration. No recipes.
    - Christmas cooky patterns: small sizes for tea cookies: [folded brochure]., circa 1940s (Box 35, Folder 21)
      Item [21] promotes Swans Down flour and Calumet Baking Powder. Includes Christmas cookie patterns; recipe with tea cookie and Christmas tree cookie variations; and directions for cutting out, decorating, and hanging on tree. Recipe uses products.
- Leavening Agents
  Series 2: Leavening Agents includes materials promoting yeast, baking powder, and sodium bicarbonate (baking soda). Publications date from 1879-1995. Those focused on yeast primarily date from 1920s-1930s and after 1970. Some notable corporate authors include Fleischmann & Co., Red Star Yeast and Products Company, National Yeast Co., Northwestern Yeast Company, and Golden Gate Compressed Yeast Company.
  There is stronger late-19th and early-20th century representation among those focused on baking powder, with most publications dating from the 1890s-1940s. Some notable corporate authors include Calumet Baking Powder Company, Cleveland Baking Powder Company, Davis Baking Powder Company, Pure Baking Powder Co., Royal Baking Powder Company, Rumford Baking Powder Col, and Warner Baking Powder Company.
  Baking soda (sodium bicarbonate) is less-well represented, but notable publications include numerous titles from the 1900s-1930s promoting Arm & Hammer baking soda, including editions of Arm & Hammer Soda Book of Valuable Recipes, Friend in Need: Facts Worth Knowing about Arm & Hammer Baking Soda as a Proven Medicinal Agent, and Good Things to Eat Made with Arm & Hammer.
  - Box 37
    Universal Foods Corporation. Red Star Yeast & Products.
    Standard Brands Incorporated.
    Burns Philp Food, Inc.
    - Kate Smith's favorite recipes. 47 p., 1939 (Box 37, Folder 1)
      Item [1] promotes Swans Down Cake Flour and Calumet Baking Powder and sponsors of Kate Smith hour on CBS Radio. Includes pictures of Kate Smith demonstrating baking techniques; cake baking hints attributed to Kate Smith and Swans Down-Calumet kitchen; product packaging and serving suggestion illustrations; questions and answers; cookbook and baking tool offers; and index. Sample recipes: peanut cream silver cake, enchanted cream sponge cake, and delicious coconut squares.
    - Kate Smith's favorite recipes: anniversary edition, 2nd ed. 47 p., 1940 (Box 37, Folder 2)
      Item [2] promotes Swans Down Cake Flour and Calumet Baking Powder, sponsors of Kate Smith hour on CBS Radio, and commemorates the show's third anniversary. Contents are similar to [1] with a few different pictures, techniques, and recipes. 2 copies.
    - Igleheart Brothers., circa 1948 (Box 37, Folder 3)
      Item [3] relates history of Igleheart Brothers and Igleheart Mills, original makers of Swans Down flour. Includes pictures of brothers, grist mill, 1900 factory, 1898 advertisement, and 1904 grand prize, St. Louis World Fair. Photocopy, p. 8-9 (source unknown).
    - Spring and summer fun with yeast. 28 p., circa 1940s (Box 37, Folder 4)
      Item [4] promotes Red Star Yeast. Includes special occasion menus and baking hints. Sample recipes: peda (Armenian bread), crunchy top coffee cake, and horns of gold. Text is typewritten.
    - Baking with self-rising flour and corn meal. 95 p., 1967 (Box 37, Folder 5)
      Item [5] promotes self-rising flour and corn meal. Recipes are from Baking Basics, teacher's reference book, copies available for $1 each. Includes information on self-rising products, serving suggestion illustrations, and index. Sample recipes: herb batter puffs, mincemeat muffins, Georgia hushpuppies, and orange black walnut drops.
    - CoolRise yeast baking, the Rapidmix way: [folded brochure]., 1971 (Box 37, Folder 6)
      Item [6] promotes Robin Hood Flour and Fleischmann's Yeast through educational materials. Includes illustrated baking techniques in large format and teaching guide.
    - [General Mills bakery flour: brochures]., 1995 (Box 37, Folder 7)
      Item [7] promotes General Mills flours in eight 8.5 x 11-inch 3-hole punched brochures. Includes serving suggestion and product packaging illustrations; product descriptions; codes for ordering; and recipes for crusty and artisan breads. Marked: CSK-5701 RTK 500M.
    - Turn to sandwiches. 18 p., 1957 (Box 37, Folder 8)
      Item [8] promotes bread use through sandwich recipes for all occasions. Includes serving suggestion and cartoon illustrations and American Institute of Baking seal.
    - Fleischmann's bake-it-easy yeast book. 62 p., 1972 (Box 37, Folder 9)
      Item [9] promotes Fleischmann's Yeast and other Standard Brand products. Includes baking hints; illustrated techniques; serving suggestion and product packaging illustrations; and index. Sample recipes: cracked wheat bread, poppy seed braid, piquant cheese loaf, and Bohemian fruit buns. Marked: Y-9871-4/72.
    - When you bake with yeast. 32 p., circa 1950s (Box 37, Folder 10)
      Item [10] promotes Fleischmann's Yeast and other Standard Brand products. Includes history of baking; baking hints; breads from around the world; illustrated techniques; serving suggestion and product packaging illustrations; and index. Sample recipes: brioche, clover leaf rolls, orange coffee cake, and sweet dough. Marked: G-771.
    - Fleischmann's Yeast: best-ever breads. 79 p., 1993 (Box 37, Folder 11)
      Item [11] promotes Fleischmann's Yeast. Includes 125th anniversary seal (since 1868); history of Fleischmann's Yeast; baking hints; illustrated techniques; serving suggestion and product packaging illustrations; bread machine hints with high altitude instructions; and index. Sample recipes: ham 'n' Swiss loaf, quick pan rolls, lacy valentine cake, and overnight cornmeal rolls.
    - Fleischmann's Yeast rising times: bread machine newsletter for food professionals. Vol. 1 (Fall 1993). 9 p. (Box 37, Folder 12)
      Item [12] is a bread machine newsletter sponsored by Fleischmann's Yeast. Includes advertisement for Fleischmann's Bread Machine Yeast; attributed testimonials; article reprint from The Japan times; Fleischmann 125th anniversary article promoting [11]; serving suggestion and product packaging illustrations; and index. Notes Norman Rockwell illustrated advertisements from 1920s.
    - Fleischmann's Yeast rising times: bread machine newsletter for food professionals. Vol. 2 (Spring 1994). 9 p. (Box 37, Folder 13)